<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the estate of clothing now vsed within this realme of England 1 The royaltie and benefit of wooll and woollen cloth. 2 The condition of the makers, being two sorts. 3 The antiquitie and power of the alneger. 4 The manner of search and searchers, now vsed. 5 The seuerall faults and abuses practised in cloth. 6 The inconuenience and hurt by the abuses. 7 The remedie to be made by the alnegers prouision. VVith an apologie for the alneger, shewing the necessarie vse of his office. Written by Iohn May, a deputie alneger.</title>
            <author>May, John, fl. 1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120174</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855373</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855373</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20863</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07323)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20863)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 895:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the estate of clothing now vsed within this realme of England 1 The royaltie and benefit of wooll and woollen cloth. 2 The condition of the makers, being two sorts. 3 The antiquitie and power of the alneger. 4 The manner of search and searchers, now vsed. 5 The seuerall faults and abuses practised in cloth. 6 The inconuenience and hurt by the abuses. 7 The remedie to be made by the alnegers prouision. VVith an apologie for the alneger, shewing the necessarie vse of his office. Written by Iohn May, a deputie alneger.</title>
                  <author>May, John, fl. 1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Adam Islip,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of cloth and clothing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wool industry --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20863:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20863:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A DECLARATION OF THE ESTATE OF CLOTHING NOW VSED WITHIN THIS REALME OF ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> The Royaltie and benefit of Wooll and Woollen Cloth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The Condition of the Makers, being two ſorts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The antiquitie and power of the Alneger.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> The manner of ſearch and Searchers, now vſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> The ſeuerall faults and abuſes practiſed in Cloth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> The inconuenience and hurt by the abuſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> The remedie to be made by the Alnegers prouiſion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>With an Apologie for the Alneger,</hi> ſhewing the neceſſarie vſe of his Office.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by IOHN MAY, a deputie Alneger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON Printed by ADAM ISLIP,</hi> An. Dom. <hi>1613.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20863:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20863:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE MOST NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince Lodwick Duke of Lenox, Earle</hi> of Darnely, Baron of Torbolton, Metheuen, and Aubig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>Lord high Admerall and Chamberlein of Scotland, Knight of the moſt noble order of the garter, and one of the Kings Maieſties moſt honorable priuie councell, and his Highneſſe Alneger generall for the Realme of England and the Dominion of Wales.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eeing for a time reſtrained from that ſeruice, which I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured to performe vpon ſome occaſion well knowne to your grace, My loue and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which no cauſe can obſcure, preſents it ſelfe with a ſubiect of your gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, often by your Graces coſt and conſent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined by mee; whoſe condition ſhall bee truely reuealed, leauing the cenſure thereof to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and wiſe conſideration, my ſelfe ſtanding by to accuſe it of many defects, who might bee
<pb facs="tcp:20863:3"/>drawne backe in baſhfull manner when I looke into myne owne impefection in wanting ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie to deliuer this cauſe in the right nature, but knowing that truth ſeemes beautifull al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though naked, and preſuming on your honourable diſpoſition, which is euer more readie to forgiue than ſharply to reproue harmeles ſimplicitie, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldens me to goe forward although in rude ſort; wherin your grace may not epect an exquiſit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but like a plaine mans tale before a Judge, which will more ſauour of trueth than elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, nor doe I take the helpe of any other to prompt mee, but onely ſeuen yeares experience, which I haue imploied in this ſubiects acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and now compiled the ſame into ſeuen howers ſtudie, for one howers relation, and ſo made it my firſt fruits for this manner of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing, which I humbly intreat to bee ſhrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder your gratious fauour. The cauſe which procures mee to this taske is two fould: Firſt, (according to my dutie) to acquaint your grace with the eſtate of the buſineſse: And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly to ſtirre your aide in the redreſse, your power beeing able to reforme, and your place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring it, ſtill in all humbleneſſe deſiring to haue
<pb facs="tcp:20863:3"/>all imperfections ouerpaſsed with your graces fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and not called into a ſtrict examination. The widowes mite was ſmall, but acceptable in regard it was all ſhee had; let not the abilitie, but the affection be called in queſtion, which wiſheth his power farre greater, onely to ſhew it all in your graces ſeruice to whom he is ſo perpetuall and irreuocable bound vnto, as all is too little he can performe, wiſhing your grace all worldlie content, and after this life all heauenlie ioyes, to guerdon your happie and honorable deeds.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces mest humble and deuoted ſeruant. <hi>IOHN MAY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20863:4"/>
            <head>To the courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I muſt confeſſe that my ouerdaring attempt, deſerues a diſgracefull checke, who like <hi>Icarus,</hi> with waxen wings hath ſoard ſo high, but that the ſun beames haue beene fauourable, my downfall might be as ſodains: this preſident is none of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and beeing ſo farre vnfit intend not to make it my pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctize. An extraordinarie cauſe compels me to this worke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you muſt expect an explanation by an Alneger and not by an Oratour: and as I moſt deſire the good opinion of the best, who doe alwaies cenſure well, ſo I leaſt regard the taunts of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſort, who commonly carpe at all. If amongſt theſe rude weeds, you can gather any wholſome herbes to ſerue your vſe I ſhall then gaine what I moſt ſought for. I am the more inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to aduenture becauſe this veſſell is bound to that port, where yet noe other hath beene before mee with like lading, whoſe better beautified wares had ſpoilde my market: yet haue I trauelled as much to collect, and beene as carefull in the choiſe of this fraight as any whatſoeuer: and imagine that he which in this, trades farther, ſhall deale for a doubtfull gaine, beeing commoditie not vendible for all, but rather vtterly reiected by ſome, yet good hope may drawe them on, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that the ſame ſort, or the leaſt companie and worſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, who knoweth not that from one flower the Bee drawes hony and the Spider poyſon, and that the content of the good, is the contempt of the euill: Therefore my reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution is ſet, hap how it wil, if the voiage miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie I am not the firſt whom hope hath deluded, but will ſtriue to reſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied howſoeuer. And ſo I take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to his power, <hi>IOHN MAY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20863:4"/>
            <head>THE ROYALTIE and benefit of Wooll and Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len <hi>Cloth.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE antiquitie of Woll with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Kingdome hath beene, beyond the memorie of man, ſo highly reſpected for thoſe many benefits therein, that a cuſtomable vſe hath alwayes been obſerued to make it the ſeat of our wiſe learned Iudges in the ſight of our noble Peeres, within the place where all whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lawes are eſtabliſhed for the good gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this kingdome,<note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment houſe.</note> to imprint the memorie of this worthie commoditie within the mindes of thoſe firme Supporters and chiefe Rulers of the Land, who euer from time to time haue with greateſt care prouided for the maintenance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as a bleſſing ſent from Almightie God vpon this nation more than all the people in the world, whoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20863:5"/>mercie in preſeruation of thoſe cattell is ſhowne by the ſuppreſſion of rauening Wolues and deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring beaſts (enemies to thoſe harmeleſſe and vnreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting flockes) which other countries, to their great dammage, doe harbour vnremedileſſe: ſo that no kingdome whatſoeuer can ſpeake ſo happily of this benefit as this realme, who findeth it the rich mans increaſe, and the poore mans comfort, in ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent nature, the quantitie ſo much as ſerueth all nations in the world, and the qualitie ſo good, as is chiefely deſired of all, working a generall fame, and moſt profitable traffique to this Land, that it may be rightly called, The Engliſh India. The depth of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit in this royall commoditie, was a long time ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured within this kingdom through ignorance and negligence of our people in thoſe dayes, who ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the tranſportation therof vnto a more ingenious nation, which made farre greater benefit by their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, than thoſe whom God had freely ſent it vnto: For when it was conuerted from the ſheeps backe, fit for mans back, it was returned by them to this realm at a treble rate, onely increaſed by their induſtrie; which ſhameful courſe brought great ſcandal of our idleneſſe: Like men that would lay no hand to the plough, and women that would ſet no hand on the wheele, deſeruing the cenſure of wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi> Hee that would not labour ſhould not eat. But leaſt I ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nne too farre in the judgement hereof, I doe call both their ignorance and negligence in queſtion not knowing which was greater; but rather
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20863:5"/>impute it to their ignorance, which appeared by the remedie procured by diuers prouident and worthie kings, who drew diuers skilfull workemen out of thoſe foreine parts, to direct theſe vnskilfull people, which in ſhort time grew perfect in this myſtery, and hath euer ſithence ſo mightily increaſed, that it is at this inſtant the glorie of our traffique, and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of our poore, many hundred thouſands de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending wholly on the ſame; chiefe pillar to our Princes reuenue, the life of our Merchant, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of our Clothier, and the meanes of ſuſtenance to moſt trades and poore, whoſe bread is gained by theſe imployments. The excellent qualitie of wooll is like moſt fertill ground that will beare all fruits, affoording the moſt ingenious wits to work vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his nature, ſo that daily new deuiſes are yeelded therby to euery inuenter. It affoords raiment, nay rich robes for the greateſt Princes, and alſo warme clothing for the meaneſt perſonages, being wroght to the height, in worth it makes rich ſilke ſeeme foreine rags; and in ordinarie manner it ſerueth the neceſſitie and vſe of all: ſo that the excrement of the worme may not compare with the fleece of the ſheepe, although the labour and induſtrie of man makes it the heigth of pride, yet in riches, comelineſſe, &amp; profitable wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it comes farre ſhort of a perfect fine wollen cloth, which although all cannot be ſo, yet all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the neceſſarie vſe of all ſorts, from the Prince to the poore, and no part vnprofitable or deceitfull in it ſelfe, but often abuſed by the wicked practiſes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20863:6"/>people, as ſhall be hereafter deſcribed, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a due reſpect of the commoditie, and care to continue the credit thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The condition of the Makers, being two ſorts.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the vſe of Clothing was planted here, ſome in all parts of the Realme vndertooke the profeſſion: The number was but ſmall for a long time, but found ſuch good ſucceſſe on their labours, as they mightily increaſed in fame and riches, chiefe comforters to the aged, and trainers vp of youth, their houſes fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented like Kings Courts, their tables repleniſhed like feaſts, their hoſpitalitie bountifull, and in all theſe their cariage plaine and honeſt, yet with ſuch plentie and content, that royall Kings haue bin high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed with their entertainment. Then was true dealing held in great eſtimation, and deceit hateful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loathed. Theſe men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly made their recourſe to London weekely, who might haue beene ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers one to another in regard of their diſtance in dwelling, yet proued brethren by reaſon of their profeſſion. Their conference of meeting was to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their credits by truth, &amp; their care how to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20863:6"/>falſhood, leaſt hee ſhould ſteale into their trades. Happieſt was he that could win moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by deſert; ſo that their marks made their markets, and their merchants their ſuiters to hold on their cuſtom. Whileſt this courſe continued the trade flouriſhed, and Gods bleſſing abounded on all dealers therein: But corrupting time (more apt in ſtooping to vice than mounting to vertue) not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infected ſome of this Fraternitie with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of deceit, but alſo ſtirred other intruders in this trade, who greedie of ſuch apparent gaine, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the well deſeruers, vſurped the name of Clothiers, without the knowledge of the true courſe, but well ſtudied in fraud, which practiſe they intended ſhould ſupply their want of knowledge, to equal that gaine formerly obtained, more reſpecting their preſent profit than all future good, nor making conſcience of the meanes, ſo they poſſeſt the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This viperous ſort doth too much increaſe in theſe daies, the onely breeders of all enormities in this trade &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealth, &amp; like caterpillers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the fruits of the earth, or like drones which waſt the honie of the labouring Bee; whoſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe muſt be preuented, or elſe in ſhort time all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits herein wil be made fruſtrat. But more of theſe abuſers when their abuſes ſhalbe in queſtion: only it may be ſaid of Clothiers, as of the tongues which <hi>Aeſop</hi> bought, the worſt meat and the beſt; ſo of the good Clothier and the bad: how lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing it is, that the priuate gaine of one ſhould
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20863:7"/>bee the preiudice of thouſands: where truth and equitie decayes the people ſoone periſh, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie it were but the law ſhould be a ſharpe bridle to curbe ſuch diſordered men. If lawleſſe libertie were allowable wee ſhould not differ from beaſts, nor diſtinguiſh good from bad: our reaſon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion leads vs to better knowledge, and daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of Gods fauour towards truth ſhould draw vs to imbrace it.</p>
               <p>We haue a preſident within this Realme to lead vs to a true courſe from that nation which were our firſt tutors to the trade, who now make a commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie among vs of our Woolls; which, by reaſon of their ſlightneſſe and ſmall value, might be eſteemed vnworthie of wearing, yet by their good obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in making, ſearching, and ſealing, it is ſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held and maintained, that it is more vendible than any cloth we make, and ſo farre voyd of deceit, that any man, although vnskilfull, may buy it without preiudice or loſſe. Looke into their liues and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, you ſhall find them religious towards God, dutifull to our Prince, louing one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and harmeleſſe to all men, onely enemies to fraud and idleneſſe, which they doe not onely hate in others, but puniſh ſeuerely in themſelues. They keepe together, and diſperſe not in many places, to the end one gouernement ſhall rule them; but in two places within this Realme doe they make their congregations,<note place="margin">Sandwich and Colchester.</note> where it were a wonder to behold, ſo many people to maintaine themſelues on ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20863:7"/>flight a trade, yet neuer a begger amongſt them. They haue no Statute Law to bind them, but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders amongſt themſelues, which are ſo duely exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, without partialitie, that their rich are not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured, nor their poore oppreſſed. Their ſearch in that commoditie is threefold, one from the Loome, one from the milling, or thickening, and one from the dreſſing; and where offence is made, there pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is ſure. What would theſe people doe if they had the making &amp; ordering of our rich clothes of great value, that can bring ſuch ſlight ware in that eſtimation? But as wee are farre from inuenting good, ſo are we vnapt to imitate it, though neuer ſo plainely taught vs before our eyes.</p>
               <p>It hath beene ſeene that a foreine cloth being made, and not falling out to the full goodneſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, the maker hath affixed a peece of ſiluer to that peece, of ſuch value as ſhould counteruaile the want of worth: But we are more readie in greedie manner to take away from a cloth, when it is too bad before.</p>
               <p>Now as herein the Clothier and maker is taxed, the Marchants and buyer cannot eſcape vntouched; For as there are good of both ſorts (whoſe number are too few) ſo there are extreame bad (which, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out amendment, might be well ſpared): There is no more difference betweene a bad Clothier and a bad Merchant, than betweene a theefe and his receiuer; for as the one commits vnlawfull crimes, the other maintaines it by concealements, nay more, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20863:8"/>him thereunto. Many Merchants are of that diſpoſition, that they more reſpect their preſent gain than the good of all others, looking vpon the cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not on the goodneſſe of what they buy; caſting vpon their gaine of mony, and not on their gaine of credit, whereas both might eaſily be obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Let a Clothier haue a new trick of deceit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to law, and preiudiciall to the generall good, if it may be a particular profit, although not dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that man ſhalbe ſure of entertainement: if hee feare diſcouerie, or to bee caught by the law, theſe Merchants haue infinit deuiſes to make it walke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible; if <hi>Argus</hi> eyes were watchfull ouer them, yet haue they miſts to blind them all: But God, who is the vpholder of truth, wil one day bring theſe hidden miſchiefes to light, and turne this wicked gaine to ſhame and loſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20863:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 3.</hi> The antiquity of the Alneger with his power.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore the making of Cloth within this Land, the Alneger was ordained, who exerciſed that office vpon al cloths com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from foreine parts, to meaſure and trie them where they were put on la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of his name Alneger ſhewes the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his office as onely meaſurer appointed.<note place="margin">2. Ed. 3, cap. 14.</note> For a long time his authoritie was caried by proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before any Parliament was holden: his fee was not then giuen him, but allowance from the Lord Treaſurer and Barons of Eſchequer, according to his paines and care: his charge was to ſee all clothes of aſſiſe marked, and thoſe not of aſſiſe and defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue, to bee taken into his hands for the King,<note place="margin">2. Ed. 3. cap. 14.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in the preſence of any Maior, Bailife, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther magiſtrate, wherein his credit and truſt repoſed by the King was explaned.</p>
               <p>When the making of thoſe Clothes were drawne hither, and dayly increaſed, the King found great loſſe in his cuſtomes; for that the wools of thoſe Clothes being before tranſported, did yeeld much cuſtome, and the like anſwered vpon returne
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20863:9"/>of the Cloth, which double benefit to the king was loſt, although it brought much good to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth by the ſubjects imployment. Vpon due conſideration hereof, a ſubſidie was graunted vnto the king and his ſucceſſours vpon all Clothes made within the Realme, foure pence vpon euerie cloth, and two pence on euerie halfe Cloth: beſides, a Subſidie vpon all graine colours,<note place="margin">27. E. 3. cap. 14.</note> as appeareth by that Statute at large: the collection whereof was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to the Alneger, as the moſt fitteſt man for it, being the kings onely officer for thoſe affaires: at which times he had alſo his fee of a halfepenie on euerie Cloth giuen him, with a reſeruation of all his former power and charge both for the king and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of abuſes.</p>
               <p>Now it is to be conſidered what value a halfepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie was in thoſe dayes, and what the ſeruice was to be performed for it: All the paynes he tooke, was but to caſt a Lyne of ſeuen yards foure times ouer the Cloth in length, and to meaſure the bredth then appointed, which he continued a long time: then were the faults but few, and eaſily-ſuppreſt; but in time grew like <hi>Hydras</hi> heads, in cutting off one, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſprung vp in the ſtead, that the defects num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred ſo faſt vpon him, as put him to endleſſe trouble.</p>
               <p>And in regard his place ſtood vpon two diſtinct of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, the one to collect the Suſidie, wherein was no farthing charge; the other was the executing of the Alnage, which tied him by great penalties to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20863:9"/>truely: he finding the paines ſo much to make reformation in ſo many defects, and of ſuch diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, with his fee too ſmall to counteruaile his dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and trouble, did voluntarily forgoe the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his office, and onely betooke himſelfe to the collection of the Subſidie: and hauing two Seales appointed him ſeuerally, one with the kings armes for the Subſidie, the other with the true content and ſearch for the Alnage, he would afterward onely ſet on the kings ſeale, leauing his ſearch and fee, to be freed of his prejudice; which neglect of his gaue way to thoſe which practiſed thoſe deceipts, and in time grew to that highth, as the whole common wealth felt the ſmart thereof; and forced all ſorts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayning to thoſe trades to ſeeke for redreſſe, and to make ſeuere Lawes for the puniſhment of thoſe deceits, appointing ſearchers and ouer-ſeers for that purpoſe, with diuers orders concerning the ſame; and perceiuing that the ſmall fee of the Alneger cauſed him to neglect the ſearch, the fee was aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented from a halfepenie to two pence, and ſo for a time carefully executed: but the former miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, which cauſed the prouiſion of thoſe Lawes and orders, in ſhort time crept in againe, more daungerous, and the office of ſearch worſe exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted with the fee of two pence than before with the Alnegers farthing: better it were ſuch ſearch ſhould bee forborne, than ſo faſlly perfourmed, nor will it euer be truely executed but by the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, who hath euer brought all queſtions and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20863:10"/>puniſhment vpon all faults yet brought to light. The Alneger is fitteſt for that place conſidering his credit and truſt with the Kings Seale, which hee is made Chauncellor of for that purpoſe, and that all the imputation of falſe Cloth and falſe ſealing is laid vpon it; ſo that both our nation and our Kings imperiall armes are ſcandalized in all foreine parts. How carefull haue former Kings been to haue the Alneger ſufficient in all points:<note place="margin">1. R. 3. cap. 8.</note> Firſt to bee expert in knowledge, then ſufficient in wealth, and that no Alneger of any Countie or Citie ſhould bee leſſe worth than an hundred pounds, if hee were of ſuch value, to the King; and in thoſe daies his credit was little inferiour to moſt of the Iuſtices where hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode: Then had hee his priuiledge to make his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts but once a yeare, whatſoeuer was in his hands: And ſo fauoured, to paſſe thoſe accomps in his highneſſe Eſchequer, without charge or fee: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides he muſt be the Kings naturall ſubiect, no alien to bee permitted thereunto. This was intended for thoſe that did execute the place: but for thoſe which ſhould receiue the reuenue and profits royall, choiſe hath been made of ſuch, as appeares vpon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, that the Queen of this Realme and the duke of Buckingham hath been intereſſed therein for ſome part of the Kingdome. And in euerie Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment where ſtatutes were ordained, the Alnegers power and priuiledge ſtill preſerued: this charge, credit, truſt, and prouiſion muſt of force drawe his care beyond thoſe ſlight ſearchers of ſmall credit:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20863:10"/>But the offendors and thoſe which practiſe deceit, thinke the Alneger too buſie in his place, ſeeking to ſuppreſſe, his power by all meanes they can. There was of late yeres a notorious felo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within this realm, who hauing committed many vnlawfull outrages, and deſirous to continue ſo, would haue the Lord chiefe Iuſtice bound to the peace, offering to take his othe that hee did not onely ſeeke to depriue him of his meanes of liuing but alſo ſought his life; ſo if they could bind the Alneger to the peace, they could make a trade of falſhood without controle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But by too much ſufferance of this hurt, the common wealth is wounded, the beſt ſort ſeeking meanes to heale it, but they like gald-backe Iades, kicke at thoſe which come to cure them. The gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſnuffers of the law is put into the Alnegers hand, who muſt make vſe of them, and howſoeuer they ſnuffe, hee will ſnuffe too, and cleere the light which ſhall ſhew them the way to trueth. In this he ſhall ſtirre vp the ſting of enuious tongues whoſe venome cannot hurt him, but procure the praiers of the beſt which ſhall receiue comfort thereby.</p>
               <p>The moſt reuerent Diuine, if he touch the finnes of the wicked to the quick, ſhall ſooner moue them to railing than to reformation, but the malice of euil people is not to be regarded. Here might queſtion bee made, wherefore the Alneger ſhould now ſtirre more than of late times: It was his vſuall courſe, to take his money for the ſeale and ſo to bee quiet: Why ſhould he trouble himſelfe with ſuch labour
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20863:11"/>that will breed enuie to him, and vexation to others. It muſt be aunſwered that although hee hath long time lyen a ſleepe, the neceſſitie of the time, and loud clamours of abuſes hath awakt him. His charge and duetie to the office, his ſeruice to the King, his maintenaunce of the trade that muſt mayntaine him, and benefit to the common wealth, ſets him on foot to performe that which no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can doe: wherein hee will ay me at two things, the general good, and his priuat profit. Since his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance much power and profit hath been drawne from him by vſurpation, which he may eaſily reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, as braunches pluckt from his bodie. The meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſilke, linnen, yea and of ſome ſorts of wollen cloth, are made petty offices, and held by thoſe which haue no right thereunto. Euerie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Magiſtrate will take vpon him to eſtabliſh offices, which ſhall contradict the appointment of the King and his Lawes. Who is the meaſurer of all ſaleable Clothes, or all commodities mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable, but onely hee? not onely appointed by ſeuerall Statutes, but alſo confirmed by the kings graunt by letters patents. It is appointed an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice at the common Law,<note place="margin">1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I. 2.</note> by graunt from the king: And that the Warden of the Alnage ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer yearely to the Lord Treaſurour the eſtreates of his office, containing all the faults hee found of Clothes throughout the Realm: The ſame King did alſo graunt the Alnage of all Canuas and linnen cloth to Tho. Dewight, in the 1. yere of his raigne,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20863:11"/>and afterward in the fourteenth yere of his raigne to one Symond of Darlington, and alſo another patent for the Alnage of all manner of outlandiſh Cloth, to one Iohn Griffen in the ſeuenteenth yere of his raigne, as may appeare vpon the ſeuerall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords in the Tower of London. If the Alneger did but a while forbeare his collection of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie alſo, ſome forged authoritie would lay claime to that too; but ſufferance cannot ſuppreſſe right, the one office being as truely due as the other,<note place="margin">25. E. 3. cap. 1.</note> and ſo many Lawes to confirme it, which alſo bindes him vpon othe to performe it: who ſhall then deny or contend againſt him when hee ſhall claime his right and performe his place? As he may receiue both ſubſidie and alnage vpon all ſorts of woollen commodities, ſo may hee receiue the alnage fee vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all other ſorts of Cloth and commodities mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable and ſaleable, from the fineſt ſilk to the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt hempe: much of that due is taken in ſome places fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, which muſt giue way when he pleaſe to take place: nor ſhall he need much difficultie to decide that right being ſo appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; plaine in his behalfe: at all times when queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath bin made of his right or power, the leaned Iudges of this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d haue confirmed the ſame, as appeareth by many ſeueral decrees. The antient laws made for alnage cauſes, may fitly be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the wil &amp; teſtament of deceaſed kings, who bequeathed to their ſubiects the benefit of iuſtice and vpright dealing, wherein the Alneger is made
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20863:12"/>ſole executor: and although by ſome later lawes there hath been ſearchers apointed as ouerſeers to aſſiſt the Alneger in the better performance of this will, they like idle and careleſſe miniſters, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the courſe of ſuch ouerſeers put in truſt, haue ſuperficially paſt ouer that charge to no purpoſe, but rather looking after their legacie of two pence on a cloth: the which the Alneger muſt abridge them of as vnworthie by their negligence to receiue it, and hee himſelfe take vpon him to ſee the will performed, beeing held thereunto by three princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall reaſons: Firſt, the truſt from the King with his ſeale, and collection of his Subſidies, Fines, and Forfeitures: Secondly, his charge not to ſet on that ſeale but vpon perfect and ſizable cloth, and to take the contrarie into his hands for the kings vſe: Thirdly, his daunger of the penaltie, if hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme not this charge, which are great fines, and the loſſe of his place: So hee muſt bee the man to giue vnto the ſubiect length, breadth, weight, and goodneſſe, or elſe to puniſh the offendor, and giue the buyer knowledge of the fault; For want hereof he is moſt taxed and blamed on all parts, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſt cauſe, for where ſhould this benefit be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceined, but from him beeing authoriſed, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the ſame. To conclude, his ſeruice true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed herein would proue a large fountaine of good, to his ſmall drop of benefit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:20863:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> The manner of ſearch and ſearchers now vſed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Law hath effectually proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the ſearch in all points, that in euerie place where cloth is made and fold, two, foure, ſix, or eight ſhall bee appointed for the ſearch thereof, that it be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to law. Thoſe ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to bee able and ſufficient in wealth and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that they ſhall be ſworne to doe it vprightly? and bound in fortie pounds a peece, not to neglect it, that they ſhal performe that ſearch, once in euery moneth at the leaſt, and enter into the houſes, ſhops, or other places which harbour any cloth, there to feeke for faultie cloth which might otherwiſe bee concealed or hidden from them, and great penaltie laid on thoſe which ſhall reſiſt or denie any of them. For thoſe clothes which are ſealed by them, the law directs their order, appointing the ſeuerall penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties on euerie fault, and how the ſame ſhall bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. If the Magiſtrates or Iuſtices of any place neglect the choiſe of ſuch ſearchers, then a penaltie is laid on them for that default: But this ſearch and orders are groſſely abuſed in ſeueral kindes. In many places are no ſearchers at all appointed: In ſome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20863:13"/>places the Clothiers and makers keepe a ſearched ſeale of their owne, to ſet on what they pleaſe: but in moſt places thoſe ſearchers choſen are vnſufficient in knowledge to performe their place, or in ability to anſwere the penalties; if they be of knowledge, then are they ſuch which be ſeruants, or workmen to thoſe Clothiers or makers which are the offenders, whom they dare not puniſh nor offend: and to auoide their breach of oath, will ſend boies or other like people to performe their place, and ſet on the ſeale; elſe will they lend that ſeale to euerie one which demands it, by which meanes they ſaue their oathes in ſeeing no faults, and for their bonds they prouide for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of them, by a combination betweene the Clothi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers &amp; themſelues, none can challenge them, but thoſe which will keepe their counſell; when any choiſe is to be made, then are the clothiers ſuiters to the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for ſuch men as they nominate, which are accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their owne hearts, which requeſt of theirs is ſeldome denied: So there are often choſen Taylors, glouers, tanners, butchers, ſmiths, or ſuch like, which haue no judgement at all in Cloth, nor the place. If malefactors of the Law might chuſe their Iudge and Iurie, they would ſeldome be caſt. The beſt ſearch made by the ſearchers in any place, is but to caſt the Clothes into ſkales to ſee if they be weight or no, which if any do want, the clothier ſupplies that want with ſtones, bricks, lead, leaden weights, and other ponderous things which they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uey into light cloth to make it hold weight, which is eaſily done in regard
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20863:13"/>thoſe cloths brought to their beame, are alwais made vp hard with tacking and binding, that without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening, thoſe deceits cannot be found, which they neuer doe, yet ought to ſee the cloth quight through from end to end, and to notifie the faults vpon the ſeale. If by chance a fault appeares vnto them which they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not auoid, ſeeing, for they ſtriue to let al paſſe in ſuch ſort as their knowledge ſhold not be charged then do they puniſh the clothier for that fault, as the Frier whipt the Nun with a Fox taile, but there is not one fault amongſt a thouſand called in queſtion. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if queſtion be made in ſome places, then doth the Major there take vpon him more than the Lord Treaſurer, to determin the cauſe, claiming a right vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all theſe ſorf. due to them, and ſo as it were hold an exchequer in euerie pettie town: in other places, the Iuſt. of Peace decide thoſe cauſes at their quarter ſeſſions, and ſo complaints paſt ouer according as the offendors make friends with them. To maintaine this authoritie, they take hold o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſtatute of 39 <hi>El. c.</hi> 20. But that branch is repealed by 4. <hi>Iac. cap.</hi> 2. yet ſtill by them put in practiſe. One principal thing is to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, That ſo many thouſands of defectiue cloths made within this realme, as the ſmart thereof is too truely found, yet are there none preſented in the kings Majeſties Exchequer, but the abuſes ſtill main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, the common wealth wronged, the king de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of his benefit, and the offendors eſcape with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out puniſhment, all this is certaine, and well knowne to all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:20863:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> The ſeuerall faults and abuſes practized in Cloth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N diſcouering of deceit, ſome cauilling humour may obiect, it will rather ſerue for inſtruction to farther practize than preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to future harme. It is aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that thoſe practitioners in theſe abuſes are ſo deepely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced therein, beeing in common vſe of them, as all other wits can giue them no more direction. The purpoſe heere intended, is to vnmaske the face of falſhoode: which ſeemes that it is not, and to giue knowledge thereof to thoſe that are wronged. The art of Conycatching was a ſecret Myſterie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till a booke of diſcouerie came forth, which could not teach them who were perfect in their leſſon without booke, but cauſe the ſimple to ſee, and the wiſeſt to ſhunne their ſubtle ſnares prouided to catch their gulls. The cauſe heere handled is nothing inferiour to theirs in cunning, but much more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them in preiudice, by the many more in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber which feele the ſmart therof; wiſhing this briefe relation might ſo effectually reueale the deceits, as it might publiquely bee knowne aſwell no thoſe which indure the damage as them which commit
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20863:14"/>the crimes: and although euery particular fault can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee heere deſcribed, by reaſon of their numbers (which were too tedious) yet the principals ſhall bee touched vpon which the reſt depend: hee that ſeeth a tree may eaſily viewe the bodie but hardly number the leaues, but the tree beeing fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the leaues ſoone die.</p>
               <p>Herewithall a difference muſt bee noted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the opinion of ſome people, and the true intent of the law. There are many ſorts of cloth or ſtuffes lately inuented, which haue got newe god fathers to name them in fantaſticall faſhion, that they which weare them, know not how to name them, which are generally called newe draperie, what hold canne the lawe take of them? In the firſt lawe, the cloth raye was vnderſtood and colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red clothes what ſizes they ſhould contain in length and breadth; ſince that time prouiſion made by lawes, for broad clothes, kerſies, dozens, peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, cottons, and ſuch like to containe length, breadth, and weight appointed: but theſe new deuices are out of the reach of thoſe lawes, and free to bee made as it ſhall pleaſe the maker with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction. To anſwere the ſame, the brigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and ground is to bee vnderſtood, the wooll paies ſubſidie, and the leugth of euerie peece al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes alnage, and although the conuerting of wools (whoſe condition yields to diuers inuentions) be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered from clothes to ſtuffes, ſhal the king loſe his ſubſidy, or the Alneger his ſee? no, it was long time
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20863:15"/>ſince ordained by ſtatute, that all ſorts of clothes, although not of aſſiſe, ſhould pay ſubſidie and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. And now of late yeres, the ſaid new deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are growne to that quantitie as the old ſort of clothing is much impaired, and that greatly increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which is not to bee diſcommended, in regard it vents our woolles, and imploies our people. But if gouernement and orders were not proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to maintaine it, in ſhort time wee ſhould find that as the ſame had eaten out the auntient dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; ſo falſhood would ruyne that, and leaue the people without imployment. Why ſhould there bee a diſtinguiſhment betweene old drapery and newe, when the law allowes but one draperie: As the condition of water may bee conueied diuers waies by riuers, ſprings, conduits, wells, pumpes, fountaines, pipes, ponds, and a number of ſeuerall meanes, yet no alteration of the nature thereof; ſo may woolls bee conuerted into diuers properties: but yet the end and purpoſe of the ſame, to ſerue mans vſe and wearing as broadcloth and auntient cloth did. If wee ſhould haue a new law for euerie new name of ſtuffe now made and named, the king muſt keepe a perpetuall Parliament to ordaine for them. There was of late a mad braind felowe which came by a company of workemen that were digging vp of a well to plant a pumpe in the place; hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded who ſet them a worke, they anſwered the parſon, churchwardens, and maiſters of the pariſh; he replyed againe they vnderſtood not themſelues,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20863:15"/>for thereby they ſhould bee forced to alter their church booke, wherein it was written, Praiſe God all yee ſprings and wells, and now it muſt bee Praiſe God all yee ſprings and pumps; which fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous and vaine queſtion of his, may bee compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to their exception, which will goe no farther then the word of the law, and neuer looke to the true intent of the ſame.<note place="margin">39. El. cap. 20.</note> A Statute was lately made concerning the abuſes of clothes, wherein orders were prouided, that all ſorts of clothes ſhould be truely ſearched, and their iuſt contents of length and weight ſet vpon euerie peece with the word ſearched, vpon paine of forfeiture. This law inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the generall good and reformation of all: yet in regard there was but two counties nominated, or a certaine circuit expreſſed which did before time moſt offend in thoſe points; all offendors in other places would ſtop that lawe from going any farther.<note place="margin">43. El. cap. 10.</note> Wherefore the next Parliament fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing vnderſtanding that lawe to concerne the generall good, as well as vnto the former limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, did make the ſame act to reſpectiuely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vnto all and ſingular woollen broad clothes, halfe clothes, Kerſies, Cottons, Dozens, Peniſtones, Frizes, Rugges, and all other woollen clothes of what nature, kind, or name ſoeuer they bee, or ſhall bee made, and to bee made within this Realme to bee viewed, ſealed, ſearched, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, to penalties, in ſuch like manner and forme and to ſuch purpoſe and intents, reſpectiuely as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20863:16"/>was limited to thoſe clothes prouided for in the former lawe, now whether can thoſe newe dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries flie to ſhroud themſelues from the reach of this lawe, theit new names cannot helpe them; if they bee called by any name, the lawe takes hold of them, or of any nature to ſerue any purpoſe the law takes hold of them, they canne then pleade no pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge to free them from this law and orders, but in yeelding obedience with true obſeruance finde peace and happineſſe. The cauſe of this relation is to ſhew that ſome of theſe old deceits are practiſed in the new deuiſed ſtuffe, wherefore as needefull to be reformed as the other; &amp; ſo proceede thereunto.</p>
               <p>Woolles beeing an excellent commoditie of it ſelfe, and naturally without deceit, is commonly abuſed by mingling in diuers kinds,<note place="margin">Deceit in ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of woolles</note> ſometime fleece wools, fell wooll, and lambs wooll which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie one to an other are put together, which makes the cloth vneuen, cockley, purſey, baudy, and rewey.</p>
               <p>Then the mingling of fine floxe with long wools yet courſe, which beeing carded together doth holde ſpinning and working but moſt deceitfull in vſe and wearing. The vſe of ſhort thrums is likewiſe ſo ordered, which they take and ſhred into ſhort length, and then lay it in ſteepe in ſtrong lye or liquor which openeth the threds into wooll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, then card it with other wooll which is worſe than the flox by making more vneuen in the ſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20863:16"/>This abuſe hath been put in practize ſo intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that it is certainely knowne clothes haue been made with two parts, floxe and thrums, and but one part in wooll; which hath ſeemed good to the eye, but in the wearing ſuch weake ſtrength as would not endure a fourth part of time like the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit cloth. If any make queſtion, whether thoſe flox, thrums, or ſorts of wooll ſhould bee caſt away or not put to vſe: It is knowne that ſeuerall ſorts of commodities are appointed wherein they may bee lawfully put to vſe, and verie vendible; but they with wicked purpoſe conuert them to great gaine, but greater hurt, worſe than caſting droſſe into fine gold, which is eaſily found by the baſeneſſe, and may bee purified againe, but this abuſe is like a poyſon not found till paſt cure.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deceits in the weaning.</note> The long thrums left of broadcloth which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be wrought to that ſhortneſſe of narrow cloths, thoſe are cunningly knit together &amp; mingled with other yarne of better nature, making the one helpe out the other, for the eaſe of workemanſhip: the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience whereof is verie hurtfull, for by reaſon of the many knots in ſuch clothes, which after the ſcouring are moſt of them burled out, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſhut vp againe by the mill; but not ſo helped, but couered for a time, when this cloth comes to wearing, in ſhort time proues full of holles and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruiceable in wearing.</p>
               <p>In ſlaying of their warps they will caſt the yarne to proue fine about a foot broad by the liſtes, which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20863:17"/>is ſo far as commonly the merchant or buyer lookes into them, nor can they hauing the clothes pleigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and bound together with threds, which will ſuffer no farther ſearch into them, vnleſſe they ſhould cut them vp, which is ſeldome or neuer done, the reſt of the cloth wrapt through with a far cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer yarne verie deceiuably. A common thing it is for the weauer to couer a courſe warpe with a fine woofe, the warp beeing ſpon hard and ſmall, and the woofe ſoft and round to couer the warpe from ſight, which in the working may ſomewhat appeare, but in the wearing throughly found, that is a daiely practize eſpecially on clothes ſould rough.</p>
               <p>Beſides they haue a practize in their woofe to ſhut in a fine woofe at both ends of their cloth, which ſerueth for a muſter to ſhewe, but all the reſt of the cloth farre worſe; the ſame ends alſo are better driuen in the loome with better workemanſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deceits in the Mill.</note> When a cloth made with flox or thrums comes to the mill, who would bee a true ſearcher, and lay the fault open, if their cunning preuented it not? but they preſerue ſuch cloth by extraordinarie meanes with tallowe, pigges dung, and vrin which keeps ni the flox, and ſuffereth the thicking.</p>
               <p>If a cloth proue ſlender, and will not thick kindly in the mill by reaſon of his defects, then haue they medicine to helpe it with oatmeale and ſuch like, which will remaine in the cloth and make it ſeeme faſt and thicke in the hand, vntill it come to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20863:17"/>dreſſing, where all that ſtopping vaniſheth, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it to ſhame by the true fight of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>When a cloth wanteth ſome of his ſubſtance or allowance in yarne, which would ſoone bee found beeing cleane ſcoured, thicked, and dried, they will not ſcoure the ſame cloth cleane, but leaue a bad ſubſtance of oyle and ſeame in it, thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it vp in the ſame filth, which proueth noiſome in vſe and wearing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deceits in man king vp of clothes.</note> Whereas the vſe of tenters is altogether forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vpon rough clothes with great penalties there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon; yet in thoſe countries where thoſe rough clothes are made and ſo to bee ſolde many tenters are erected and vſed vpon ſuch clothes as ſhould bee left in that order, as it commeth out of the mill, yet by reaſon of the aforeſaid abuſes in yarne and weauing, the mill leaues them ſhamefull in cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells, baudes, purſey, narrower in ſome places than other, which they by colour to euen out, doe often ſtrain beyond the limitation allowed for dreſt cloths in deceiuable manner.</p>
               <p>When ſuch clothes haue beene ſo ſtrained, the tenter hookes leaue an euident marke vpon them alongſt the liſts, and at both endes, which would plainely tell where they had beene, and how vſed; but they haue a tricke to hide that fault, for with a wet cloth and a hotte Iron, they ouer runne thoſe liſts and ends which ſhutteth vp the marks or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20863:18"/>tongues of the tenter, as that ſhall tell no tales.</p>
               <p>If the cloth by the ſame tentring doe proue hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe in hand, then doe they alſo ouer runne the ſame cloth with that hot Iron about a ſpan deepe from the liſtes, for the binding of the cloth vp with threds keeps it from farther ſight, which deuiſe makes the cloth feele cloſe in hand in that place, howſoeuer the reſt fall out. Thoſe clothes which fall out much too light they will let hang abroad in an euening, ſometime all night, to receiue the dew, or elſe to ſpout warme water into it, which will make it weigh heauier by eight pounds, beſides, to feele more kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in hand: this is ſo cunningly done that it is hardly to bee perceiued, yet many of them ſo ouerdone therewith as they are returned againe from beyond the ſeas rotten with the ſame vſage.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deceits in dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</note> When a cloth which is made vp with flox or thrums, that it is too tender to endure due work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, thoſe clothes ſhall bee rowed drie, and wrought with ſolace and ſoft liquor to preſerue the flox from the force of the teſſell, yet make it riſe with a ground to worke vpon in ſhearing.</p>
               <p>In the tentring of cloth, which is allowed to ſtraine but halfe a quarter in breath, and a yard in length vpon a whole broadcloth: It is knowne that diuers is ſtrained a quarter and a halfe in breadth, and fiue yards in length, ſo that a cloth ſtrained to thirtie yards, beeing wet againe hath loſt aboue a third part in length and breadth.</p>
               <p>And a kerſie allowed to bee ſtrained one naile
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20863:18"/>in breadth, and halfe a yard in length and no more: It hath beene knowne that a Deuon-ſhire kerſie of twelue yards hath beene ſtrained a quarter of a yard in breadth and three yards in length: ſo that in breadth and length the tentors lends them the one halfe of the peece, which as ſoone as it comes to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter flyes away inuiſible to his owne countrie, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be found againe. The like abuſe in other ſorts of kerſie and narrowe clothes.</p>
               <p>If a cloth by much milling is run in, which may cauſe them more labour to bring vnto the length and breadth they appoint to, then will they vſe warme water in the tentring thereof, but common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the warmth of the ſunne which they alwaies ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue will make a cloth yeeld any way in ſtretching: ſo they doe make the glorious ſunne (which God hath ſent for comfort to the world) to bee acceſſary to their vild abuſe, in giuing them ſuch helpe: So doe the wicked often turne Gods beſt bleſſings into the worſt vſes.</p>
               <p>In the finiſhing of their worke of rowing and ſhearing they will vſe a deceit with flox of the ſame colour of the cloth, which they can ſheare as ſmall as duſt, which mixt with ſolace, they ſpread vpon the muſters, and where the cloth may bee ſeene, which makes it ſeeme much finer than it is, and feele more ſubſtantiall in hand; but the ſame cloth lying a while after the dreſſing, the ſolace drieth vp, and then the ſame flox flyeth away leaning the cloth in his owne nature againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20863:19"/>
                  <note place="margin">Colours.</note> For the falſe dying of colors both in woolls, cloth, and ſtuffes, with the vſe of logwood, it is intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and too common, to the great diſcredit of the thing ſo died. The ground of good colours is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall woading, without which diuers colors can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be perfectly made, as blackes, ruſſets, tawnyes, purples, greenes, and ſuch like, wherof many of them are made without foundation of woad, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth beautifull and pleaſing to the eye, but in vſe and wearing proue like falſe painting and not true dying: Some colours haue a ſlight ground of woad, but farre too weake for the depth of that colour it beares, yet can ſet vp the woade marke, or woade roſe, which is vpon the piece at a farre richer depth than the peice is woaded throughout: nay farther, ſome can ſet on a woadmarke vpon a cloth with a little Indico which hath no woade at all on the peice: but herein the diers of London doe beſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a true courſe in ſetting a woaded ſeale vpon woaded colours, which is a truer teſtimonie than the woade roſe or marke ſo many waies abuſed, yet is not the vſe of that ſeale effectually performed in this kind. There is fiue eſpeciall degrees in woading that is to ſay <hi>a huling, a plounket, a watchet, anazur, &amp; a blew,</hi> euery one of theſe exceeding each other in value, yet euery one of them fit for ſome colours: Now if theſe degrees were truely expreſſed on the woa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſeale, then might the buyer knowe the trueth of each colour, and cauſe a reformation of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable abuſe, which doth daily cauſe ſuch num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20863:19"/>of our cloths and ſtuffes, to bee caried out of the realme to bee dreſſed and died, to the great preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of many of the Kings maieſties ſubiects which might be wel maintained vpon thoſe imployments: the trueth of the colour is as materiall as the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the cloth, for as oftentimes good cloth is ſpoyled by a bad colour, ſo doth a good colour often mend and preferre a meane cloth, therefore as needefull to bee prouided for ſome:<note place="margin">Caſuall faults.</note> faults come by negligence without deceiuable intent, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time by ouermilling of a cloth through abſence of the mill-man, then is there ſome ſorts of woolles of that nature as will not proue ſo well in milling as other woolles: ſometime a cloth ouer heated with going too drie in the mill and ſo conſumed, ſometime a ſmall ſtone in the fulling earth workes many brackes or holles in the cloth, then may miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune happen by bad oyles, as Whale oyle by lying long will chaunge the colour and alter the cloth; ſometime a cloth hurt by roukling to the mill, which fault might bee well put in the mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans deceit, becauſe hee doth the ſame with cards to rake off much flox.</p>
               <p>Againe the want of the clothiers marke may ſometimes come by negligence of the weauer, but often pretended wilfully, either in regard of the falſhood of the Cloth which makes them ſhame to ſet their marke, or els intending to put ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans marke in it, which they commonly doe without weauing, ſowing the ſame being taw, and ſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20863:20"/>milled vpon it: but verie fit it is that euerie marke ſhould bee wouen in the cloth, to draw them to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect making, for the credit of their markes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deceits vſed by ſome mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</note> There are ſome merchants that deale in ſtuffes termed new draperie, eſpecially in perpetuanas, which are now growne to great vſe and traffique, but not like to continue long, by their falſhood ſince their firſt making, which brought them into eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for where at firſt their pitch in the loome was twelue hundreth, but now brought to eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth, yet keepe their breadth and length. Some of theſe merchants doe buy ſlight ſayes and put them forth to milling, and make baſtard perpetuanas of them good to the ſight, but ſo vnprofitable in wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that the ſame abuſes doe vtterly diſcredit that commoditie.</p>
               <p>A ſort of cloth is made called Mancheſter or Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire plaines to make cottons, which containe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a yard in breadth: theſe are often bought by merchants and others, which cut them in length ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a kerſie, and hath them dreſſed and dyed in forme to a kerſie, the which are not onely vented into forein parts, but many of them vented in the Realme; which cloth proues verie vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in wearing. Alſo there haue ſome merchants cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed counterfeit Deuonſhire kerſies to bee made in Yorkſhire out of waſhers or halfethicks, which haue contained ſuch length and breadth with ſtop liſts, like thoſe Deuonſhire kerſies, which they haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be dreſſed, died, &amp; preſſed with the hot preſſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20863:20"/>and ſo ſent beyond the Seas in the name of Deuon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire kerſies, to the great diſcredit of that ſort of Cloth: beſides, there is a greedie deſire in ſome mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, who cauſe the Clothier to make their cloths of extraordinarie length, that is to ſay, the ſubſtance and length of a cloth and a halfe into one cloth, &amp; if they cannot get them made ſo, then they will cut Cloths and draw three cloths into two ſo cunningly as can hardly be found: this is done, to deceiue the king of his cuſtomes and other dueties. Some Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers haue made practiſe to draw the forell of a fine Kentiſh Cloth vpon a Northen Dozen, ſo cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as could not eaſily be perceiued, which forell by the Alnegers negligence hath had the kings armes with the name of that countie vpon it, whereas he ought to ſet it within the Cloth. The ſent of thoſe Northen Dozens hath been taken away, firſt by ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and afterwards with liquors or powders: ſo the buyers haue not had onely the forels to deceiue them, but in falſe manner, the kings ſeale hath beene made vſe of to that purpoſe: and then the deceiuer to conclude all, layes his hand vpon the forell, and with an equinocating oath, ſweares this Kentiſh cloth coſt him ſo much.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a late commoditie in great vſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king within this kingdome,<note place="margin">Fuſtians.</note> which ſetteth many people on worke, called Fuſtians, which for want of gouernement are ſo decayed by falſhood, keeping neither order in goodneſſe nor aſſiſe, inſomuch that the makers thereof, in this ſhort time of vſe, are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20863:21"/>of their trades, and it is thought will return again to the place from whence it came, who doe ſtill ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue their ſorts and goodneſſe in ſuch true manner, as by their ſeales they are ſould, keeping vp the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of that which they make: what a ſhame is this to our Nation, to be ſo void of reaſon and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that a good trade ſhould bee ſuppreſſed for want of good order amongſt themſelues, and haue ſo good a preſident from others. Theſe many enormities are now in the hight of practiſe, the euill diſpoſed hauing no feeling thereof, but runne forward to the ruine of all: but to the well diſpoſed which lookes into theſe abufes, it appeares lamentable and grieuous, deſiring that a better por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be procured for thoſe offenders, to purge ſo vile and dangerous a diſeaſe, which may in ſhort time grow incurable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:20863:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> The inconuenience and hurt by theſe abuſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hileſt the true making of Cloth indured in reaſonable maner it was moſt vendible in al parts, &amp; ſo much deſired, that foreine Merchants did vſually come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this realme, to fetch them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: but ſince deceit crept in, he hath grown greater, and increaſed euery day, the trade ſtill declining from bad to worſe, and now to worſt of all, like Iuie, which being ſuffered, claſpeth the tree ſo hard, that in time the bodie dies thereby. What maketh thoſe now to refuſe our Cloth being brought to their owne dores, which before time ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſought it at ours? falſhood. What makes the Gentleman complaine of his Wooll which lyes on his hand? The clothier complaine of his dead ſales? The Merchant complaine on his loſſe? all but fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood. What will this come vnto? Nay what is it come to alreadie? The Authors of this euill, both the bad Clothier &amp; the bad merchant, are ſurfeited with their ſweet meat, like Prodigals that ſpend their patrimony in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which might wel ſerue them &amp; their poſterity: deceits ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not indure, eſpecially who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it growes violent, nor can they throw it ſo far off, but that it will rebound back to them which threw it.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20863:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:20863:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:20863:23"/>How thicke are certificats of falſhood returned vpon our Merchants from beyond the ſeas? ſo that they know no end of their trouble, nor certaine of their gaine or loſſe vntill their moneys be receiued, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batements deducted. Bad wares are the breeders of bad debts and deſperat hazards, wherewith both Merchaunts and makers are extreamely puniſht: when a complement of defectiue cloth is made, the owner is often inforced to barter for as bad a commoditie, a hilding for a Iade, or elſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer it out with a handfull of that ſweet hearbe time, but receiue it with a backe burden of the bitter hearbe Rew. So heere is aduenture increaſed, in which point the Merchant far exceeds the maker<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yet the maker is an aduenturer, who hath his goods and ſubſtance diſperſed into many hands, yea and amongſt the poorer ſort, of diuers conditions, whoſe fingers are like thornie buſhes which the ſheep muſt go through, in euerie of which, do what he can, he ſhall leaue a locke of his fleece behind him, and although he preſerue the principall, yet will a part be detained indirectly: Then when he hath with great care and time finiſht his worke, he muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe a doubtful Market, and often light on a bad mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, which defeats him of all: yet herein is his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; for his worke folke, they are within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of his view, and ſeldome faile, by reaſon of their continual dependa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; for his Markets he doth weeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know his worſt; and for his Merchant, he may daily ſee or beare from him at the Royal-Exchange,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20863:23"/>if his dealing be in London, &amp; in other places with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Realme in like manner. Wherefore, his fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards are but petie aduentures in regard of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.</p>
               <p>For when thoſe commodities are faſtned on the merchant, he muſt indure a number of dangerous aduentures, both outward and inward, ſhipwracks at Sea, peril of Pirats, and other robbers; at his place of ſale, there he muſt giue credit to thoſe hee neuer ſaw, and ſuch as neither liue in his religion nor Law, he muſt abide to anſwer all defects found, where our owne Laws ſhalbe alledged to puniſh them who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was not priuie to the offence. If they eſcape con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation, yet ſhall they be ſure of intollerable abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with bad words, and ſhamefull reproches; they muſt ſtand to the honeſty of their factors, which often proue falſe, and the daunger of the Countrie often ſubject to change. Theſe and many other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties cauſeth cares to abridge his reſt, and keepes him waking when others ſleepe, euerie ſtormie wind breedes his feare, and euerie flying report makes him doubtfull, and not without great cauſe, ſeeing ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fall ſo lainly to the vtter ouerthrow, not onely of themſelues, but diuers other depending vpon them, like to the fall of a mightie Tree, which cruſheth downe the vnder ſhrubs about him, ſo farre as his fall did reach. Therefore the chiefe remedie to preuent much of this miſchiefe, is to deale in loyall and perfect commodities, which will with credit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide his time for Market, when the other by long
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20863:24"/>lying looſeth ſtill, both in goodnes and credit; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing haſtie bargains, that brings after repentance. In Prouinces beyond the bounds of Chriſtendome, God is blaſphemed, our Religion reuiled, and our people miſtearmed in beaſtly manner: when a Turke or Infidell bruſheth his garment bare, that he may number the threeds, and find it to haue feeling fence to runne in at a wet ſhowre, or a hot Iron, then our Chriſtian profeſſion is called in queſtion by thoſe prophane people, who meaſure our faith by our works. In kingdomes nere vs, theſe abuſes haue been found ſo odious, and their people ſo much wronged, that they haue made lawes and edicts, to baniſh our cloth out of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, rather deſiring our wools, wherewith they can make true commodities. This hath ſet diuers cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries on work, in making of cloth, which ſerueth thoſe places of traffike, where we did vſe to commerce, diuers workemen haue gone out of this Land, to make vſe of their practiſe and liuing there, where they are intertained, and daily increaſe: In our owne Countrie, where much of our Wooll may bee vented, the falſhood of clothing is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that euerie one ſtriueth to weare any thing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than cloth: if a gentleman make a liuerie for his man, in the firſt ſhowre of raine it may fit his Page for bigneſſe, and for the colours and other conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in it, after a moneths wearing, it will looke like a ſouldiers coat which hath line ſixe moneths out of garriſon. It hath bin knowne that a poore man, get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſo much money together with care and trauell
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20863:24"/>as would buy him a ſuit of cloth, and taking his Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor with him, who ſeeing the cloth, hath juſtly told him how much would ſerue to make his Ierkin, and breeches which he hath bought accordingly, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards counceld by that Taylor, to caſt his Cloth in the water, to make it more ſeruiceable, which he ſo doing, hath quite loſt his Ierkin, and hauing no more money, was forced to goe cold all winter in his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per parts: this in ſome degree may be accounted ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, to rob the poore; what are the inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that are drawne on by theſe meanes? firſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie to our king, whoſe ſeale is fixt on this cloth, iniurie to our nation that workes abuſe on this cloth, infamie to our ſelues that weare ſome part of this Cloth, and vtter ruine of all benefits which ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe by this cloth. It is high time to looke out, when the fire hath caught hold of the houſe end; if it be not preuented by quenching it will ſoone conſume to the ground, and it is doubtfull whether theſe enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities are incurable or no: the plant of falſhood is grown ſo great and antient, that it may be ſuppoſed rather to breake than bend, but extraordinarie means and paines muſt be applied to the cauſe, which may be recouered by good induſtrie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20863:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The remedie to be made by the Alnegers prouiſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S this full growne euill hath now procured a daungerous hurt, ſo hath it verie happily falne out in a time which can afford an eſpeciall remedie. When this kingdome was diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded amongſt ſeuen kings, it was vnder a ſtrange gouernement: when there was twiſe ſeuen Alnegers in the realme, there was neither law nor order obſerued amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; but all they ſought was gaine, and how to intrude into each others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit: if a Clothier or offender were interrupted in his falſhood within one Countie, he could freely exerciſe the ſame in another; where he ſhould be willingly receiued, becauſe he augmented that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negers profit. But now, thankes be to God, wee liue vnder one gratious Prince, who ordaines no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of Lawes; but hath prouided one order of gouernement for all; So that ill diuided office of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage which ran to ruine in many hands, is now redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into one worthie mans hands; which hath not only power to command, but alſo will to performe all meanes, and courſes, which may tend to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of this grieuous enormitie: In this buſines
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20863:25"/>many hands muſt bee imployed, whoſe worke may ſeeme harſh to thoſe which ſhall be put out of their wonted courſe: But it is not their content that is ſought; vnto a generall good euerie perticular help muſt bee applied, heere muſt bee more paines in the Alneger, more care and truth in the workman, and more trouble to the clothier, but all to a good and profitable end. The firſt thing to bee looked vnto, is the condition of the clothiers and makers of cloth, ſtuffes, and commodities belonging to this gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which at this time is much differing from law or order, many of them vnexperienced and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers of the trade, who not being maſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of through want of knowledge commit moſt of theſe abuſes. And whereas the law prouides that none which profeſſe thoſe trades ſhould bee admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnder ſeuen yeares ſeruice in apprentiſhip, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers do come into the ſame with a moneths practize, and cloies the Kingdome with defectiue commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, beggering themſelues, and hurting thoſe which ſhould liue by the ſame: Theſe people for the moſt part dwelling in obſcure places, neuer bringing their commodities to ſearch or ſeale, nor yeelding any duetie, liue rather like outlawes than ſubiects. There is a petition vnto the Kings Maieſtie, extant from the beſt clothiers and makers in diuers parts to this purpoſe, who craue a corporation for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of this, which were pittie but it ſhould be graunted, confidering how many inferiour trades enioies ſuch priuiledge that gouerne their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20863:26"/>in good ſort and order. If this were accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, the better halfe of this great taske were finiſhed, and great hope that our generall Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger will procure it, beeing ſo good an aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to worke the reformation which lies on his charge.</p>
               <p>The diſperſing of clothiers and makers is a principall cauſe to breed theſe defects: whereas the lawe ordaines that clothing ſhall not bee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but in a citie, borough, or market towne, or elſe where clothing hath beene vſually, to the end that the eye of the officer ſhould bee vpon their doings: Now they ſcatter themſelues in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting places, and if there bee but one clothier in a pariſh hee will demaund an Alneger to attend him, if not, force the Alneger to come vnto his houſe to ſeale his cloth, where hee ſhall beſtowe twelue peny worth of labour for the earning or receiuing of one groate: and when hee comes thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee ſhall find them ſearched by his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours that hee hath cauſed to bee choſen ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, who haue no skil, or elſe by his workman who dare doe nothing but what himſelfe directeth, and if the Alneger will ſometime call their ſearch in queſtion and trie the cloth, hee ſhall neither haue place conuenient to view them, nor weights of any certaintie to weigh them, but ſuch weights as they will bring him, which ſhall bee ſtones, logges, and ſuch other things as they will tell him their weight, and hee muſt beleeue them. There is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20863:26"/>no officer vnder the king ſo much deluded &amp; abuſed as hee, beeing ſo neceſſarie for the kingdome and beneficiall to the crowne: Somtime, and in ſome places they will call him from his reſt at all houres of the night to performe his office, not for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, but of purpoſe to diſturbe him, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other iniuries, which they in baſe manner haue offered him: but herein himſelfe is moſt to bee blamed, that knowing his owne power and place would ſuffer ſuch indignities. The courſe of theſe dayes is for ſuch as will beare to haue greater burdens put vpon them than can bee borne. It is vnknowne that any officer of the Kings which hath the keeping and vſe of his ſeale ſhould bee ſubiect to ſuch ſeruitude, neither is it conuenient: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the true courſe herein to bee obſetued, is for the Alneger, to prouide in euerie place (need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for an Alnegers reſidence) a conuenient roome for all Makers or Clothiers to come vnto, wherein muſt bee a pearch to drawe ouer the clothes, a table to meaſure and trie the clothes, and a beame with true weights to weigh the clothes, and the deputie not onely to bee ſufficient in abilitie and knowledge but alſo bound, and ſworne to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his office truely, that hee ſhall bee there alwaies readie at conuenient or appointed times to make a true ſearch in all points, and in no place elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and vpon the altering of the propertie of the cloth, to make a new ſearch in theſe degrees:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20863:27"/>Firſt, if the aforeſaid corporation bee procured, that then the clothes bee firſt viewed raw by the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens or aſſiſtants of that corporation, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the cloth bee made of ſound yarne, or any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit bee wrought by the weauer, and beeing found merchantable to bee marked at the head end with a marke of allowance cut in the cloth according to the manner of ſearch now vſed vpon raw Deuon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire kerfies, but beeing defectiue either to iagge the ſame at both ends, or cut off the head forrell from the cloth, and to ſet ſuch fine vpon the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor as thoſe Wardens or Ouerſeers ſhall find the fault deſerue. But for the Alnegers charge, when the cloth is thicked from the mill to meaſure the ſame truely in length and breadth, not truſting to the clothiers content who will often for the credit of his cloth, ſet on more length than it doth true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly containe; and that the Alneger doth ſet on the iuſt content in the water, whatſoeuer it contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth on his ſeale, alſo expreſſing the the narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or other defects which hee ſhall find: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt euerie fault in the cloth to cut downe a notch of an inch deepe and therein fixe a ſeale as may appeare to the buyer where the fault is, then when this cloth is fully dried, that hee ſet one the iuſt content of weight alſo whatſoeuer it ſhall weigh, all this to bee done before the kings ſeale bee fixed thereunto.</p>
               <p>When any of thoſe clothes are farther altered by dying, dreſſing, or ſtrayning, that hee cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:20863:27"/>thoſe former ſeales of the water to remaine ſtill vpon the cloth, to expreſſe what it was, and to ſet other ſeales vpon that cloth to ſhew vnto the buyer what that cloth is ſtrained vnto accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the appointment of the Lords of his Maieſties councell which graunted a tolleration for certaine clothes to bee ſtrained, yet laid that charge vpon the Alneger, that the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the water content and ſtrained length might bee ſeene: If other faults bee in that cloth either by dying or dreſſing, that the ſame bee alſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by ſeuerall ſeales: whether that cloth be colour graine, woaded, or contrarie in falſe color, ſo that in of right it ought to haue thoſe ſeales ollowing.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 A ſeale of water length. Died clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</item>
                  <item>2 A ſeale of narrowneſſe and defects. Died clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</item>
                  <item>3 A ſearched ſeale, with the weight. Died clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</item>
                  <item>4 A ſeale for ſtrained length. Died clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</item>
                  <item>5 A ſeale for colour and dreſſing. Died clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</item>
                  <item>6 The kings ſeale and countie. Died clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And that euerie ſeale ſet on by the Alneger may haue an eſpeciall marke therein to ſignifie the place where it was ſealed, and by whom, to the end that if any defects bee paſſed ouer by fauour or negligence in him, he may bee rightly chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and puniſhed for the ſame according to his error, and that in all ſearches hee bee both pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and principall, at the rawe ſearch with the Wardens or Ouerſeers, at ſearch from the mill by himſelfe and whom hee pleaſe, at the ſearch of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20863:28"/>ſtraining and dreſſing by himſefe and ſuch worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of iudgement as hee ſhall make choiſe for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie, and for the ſearch of dying to haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the true opinion of the beſt experienced ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, both for colours died in wooll, and colours di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in cloth, and all to bee ſealed according to their true propertie.</p>
               <p>So heere is foure ſearches to bee made on a dreſſed and died cloth, three ſearches on a dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed white cloth or kerſie or of like nature, and two ſearches vpon euery rough white cloth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed: And to euerie one of theſe ſearches a fee due of two pence on euerie broadcloth, and ſo according to the rate on all other clothes to bee paied: and it may ſo happen that all theſe ſearches cannot bee performed in one place by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the cloth may bee wouen in one place, milled in an other, dreſſed in an other, and died in an other, ſo the diuerſitie of ſearch muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by ſeuerall Officers: this cannot bee auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but where the condition and propertie is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, the Officer there muſt make that ſearch, and by the ſeuerall ſeales appeare where the cloth was made, where dreſſed, and where died, and by whom in euerie ſearch ſeene and ſealed.</p>
               <p>In the maner of this ſearch hee muſt obſerue the ſeuerall penalties ordained by the law vpon all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, wherein hee muſt chiefely followe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Statute lately made in 4. <hi>Iacobi cap.</hi> 2. for length, breadth, and weight, of all ſorts of cloth,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20863:28"/>which although hee doe not proſecute with extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, yet keepe them ſo farre within gouernement, as may bring them to reformation, and the King to receiue more benefit by his lawes. The Alneger in euerie place muſt alſo keepe a booke for the King; wherein muſt bee regiſtred the ſeuerall fines and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties taken in all theſe ſearches, for what, and from whom,<note place="margin">11. H. 6. cap. 9.</note> which accompt muſt agree with the ſeale of faults by him ſet on: if any cloth proue intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable defectiue, that the Alneger then cut off the liſt or porell at the one end of that cloth that it may not bee accompted for a cloth, but a remnant, and ſo ſealed by him accordingly, taking his fees, duties, and penalties on that cloth notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>And that the Alneger procure them to publique markets, eſpecially in London according to the ſtatut of 39. <hi>Eb. cap.</hi> 20. or elſe to lay the penaltie of that law on them, which is 40. s. vpon a cloth, and by all means to preuent priuat ſales, which is the couer to hide all abuſes, &amp; eſcape due ſearch, &amp; therefore ought care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be obſerued.<note place="margin">Obiections.</note> In proſecuting this order and courſe there will bee three maine obiections made, to ſay, trouble, charge, and daunger: Firſt who will endure ſuch extraordinarie toile in carrying their goods ſo often to ſearch, and beeing in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places, farre off from the place of ſearch: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly who will yeeld-to ſuch a charge, as to the fees of a fourefold ſearch whereas heretofore neuer but one was required, and that fee hardly paid; this will be held a taxation or an impoſition vnneceſſarily
<pb facs="tcp:20863:29"/>drawne on, and good to bee auoided: Thirdly, who will run wilfully into the daunger of the lawe, as to abide the penalties which ſhall bee found out by ſo many ſearches, wherein euerie degree many offences are made. Wee cannot (ſay they) caſt our cloth in a mould, but ſhall of force offend: rather then theſe hard conditions ſhould bee vndergone, euerie man will giue ouer clothing and betake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to other courſe of liuing, what ſhall then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the trade?<note place="margin">The Anſwere.</note> To the firſt, the law requiers them to bee ſearched and further appoints them to bring their cloth to a citie, borough, or towne corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and there to bee ſearched and ſealed where the Alneger or ſealer ſhall bee, and place fitting: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,<note place="margin">4. &amp; 5. P. &amp; M. cap. 5.</note> there is a vacant time commonly with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie cloth betwixt each degree of ſearch: when a cloth comes forth of the loome, it goes not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to the mill, nor ſo from the mill to dreſſing, neither from dreſſing to dying, but ſometime a day or two, more or leſſe lieth ſtill, affording time for ſuch triall; but admit that all expedition therein may bee required, that time loſt is nothing bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoone diſpatched, neither will the paines ſeeme great to thoſe which intend trueth, better it is for them to endure a myles trauell, than the Merchants ſhould ſtill vndergoe an endleſſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, theier clothes often returned many hundred myles, and certificats daily which doth treble their loſſe euerie way: whereas by this courſe they ſhall know their worſt at home, auoyd after-recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20863:29"/>and breed eaſe &amp; benefit to the merchants and themſelues. Secondly, for the charge that cannot be forborne, if the ſeruice be performed, conſidering this, that thoſe which doe the ſame, are or ought to be of eſtimation, profeſſors of that trade: wherefore, pretious is loſſe of time, and that their paines duely done therin, deſerues no leſſe fee, but eſpecially their danger of loſſe, which will light on them, if their ſearch be falſe &amp; negligently performed. The charge of a bay, ſealed at Colcheſter (whoſe courſe herein muſt be imitated) by reaſon of the often ſearch it comes vnto ten pence duetie, yet diuers of them not aboue fortie ſhillings value: if this payment were left, their orders would fall, wherein they reape a fiue-fold benefit: ſo ſhall all Clothiers and makers find hereby, that if his cloth be defectiue, he ſhall know the worſt of his loſſe, but if it be merchantable, thoſe ſeales ſhall be ſuch credit vnto it as ſhall much aduantage the ſale thereof. Better is 8. pence giuen to haue a worke effectually done, than two pence to him that doth nothing at all, if any thing, rather hurt than good. The ſparing of this courſe, and theſe fees, hath beene the breeding of all former hurts; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the general good required it, yet euery mans priuat reſpect that ſhould perfome paines without profit, drew backe the meanes of remedie and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. 3. the daunager of Law cannot be diſpenced withall to thoſe which wilfully breake the Law: it was ordained to be obſerued, yet moderadion will be herein vſed and a difference made betweene faults
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20863:30"/>pretended, &amp; faults caſual, &amp; the puniſhment in alſo inflicted, as ſhall rather tend to procure amendment, than the offenders ruine: and for offences generall, which are all lyable to the law, moſt of them by the makers care and officers ſearch will be ſuppreſt, and all in ſhort time by endeauours on all parts quite rooted out. That a doth cannot be caſt in a mould, it is true, but a clothier skilfull and carefull in choiſe of his wool and yame, and alſo perfect in his trade, may make a cloth as it pleaſeth himſelfe in length, bredth, euenneſſe, and eſpecially in weight. We haue a ſort of Clothiers which haue tolleration to ſtraine, and whereas their clothes ſhould containe in weight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dreſſed 60. l. the tolleration allowes them at 58. which comming all to the Alnegers triall, be in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to them, pardons them at 56. which they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing to incurre no daunger, vnleſſe they be any thing vnder that weight, will bring them ſo juſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, that in 20. clothes together, you ſhal ſcarce find a quarter of a pound in any differing from 56. l. that indeed a man may judge they were caſt in a mould: theſe men could aſwell make them to 58. l. but that they ſtriue to decline, ſo farre as they can without danger. As for the diſcouraging of people to deale in this trade, when ſo ſtrict ſearch and order ſhal be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, neither the good clothier, nor the good Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, will ſay ſo, nor the general opinion eſteeme it ſo: It was neuer knowne that true gouernment did at any time decay any trade, but rather cauſed it to increaſe and flouriſh, by this meanes much more
<pb facs="tcp:20863:30"/>Cloth will be made, better ſould, and more deſired and ſought for: and to conclude, ſupplie all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie wants, which this worthie (but ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wronged) trade hath long time indured.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
